Guide to the Mathematics Department Special Programs Records, 1955 - 1971 UA.25.27.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Mathematics Department Special Programs records
1955-1971
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Mathematics Dept
UA.25.27.0001
10 Linear Feet
The Mathematics Department at Duke University has sponsored several special programs to train high school and college math teachers. Two of these programs were the Summer Institute in Science and Mathematics and the Retired Officer Program. The Summer Institute in Science and Mathematics, supported by the National Science Foundation, helped secondary school teachers upgrade their skills in the sciences and in math. The Summer Institute trained teachers from 1957-1970. The Retired Officer Program trained retired military personnel to teach mathematics in high school or at the introductory college level. It was also supported by the National Science Foundation and trained teachers from 1958-1967. The collection contains yearbooks, program records, course lists, photographs, government reports, and information about these special programs. English.
10000 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Mathematics Department Records, 1955-1971, was received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1982 (A82-86).
Historical Note
The Mathematics Department at Duke University has sponsored several special programs to train high school and college math teachers. Two of these programs were the Summer Institute in Science and Mathematics and the Retired Officer Program. The Summer Institute in Science and Mathematics, supported by the National Science Foundation, helped secondary school teachers upgrade their skills in the sciences and in math. The Summer Institute trained teachers from 1957-1970. The Retired Officer Program trained retired military personnel to teach mathematics in high school or at the introductory college level. It was also supported by the National Science Foundation and trained teachers from 1958-1967.
Collection Overview
The Mathematics Department Special Programs Records contain yearbooks, program records, course lists, photographs, government reports, and information about the Summer Institute in Science and Mathematics and the Retired Officer Program. An effort has been made to remove application letters, rejections letters, requests for information, receipts, and grades from the collection. Because many of these items are interspersed in the yearbooks and program records, some of these items may still remain and are covered by access restrictions.
Related Material
Mathematics Dept. Records, 1937-1980.
University Archives, Duke University.
Retired military personnel -- United States; Retired military personnel -- Employment; Science -- Study and teaching (Secondary); Science -- Study and teaching (Higher); Science -- Study and teaching -- United States; Yearbooks; Mathematics; Mathematics -- Study and teaching (Higher); Photographs; Mathematics -- Study and teaching (Secondary); Mathematics -- Study and teaching -- United States; National Science Foundation (U.S.); Duke University. Mathematics Dept; Duke University. Mathematics Dept. Retired Officer Program; Duke University. Mathematics Dept; Duke University. Mathematics Dept. Summer Institute in Science and Mathematics
- Summer Institute in Science and Mathematics, 1955-1970
  Scope and Contents note
  The Summer Institute in Science and Mathematics, supported by the National Science Foundation, was a group study program designed to help secondary school teachers upgrade their skills in the sciences and in math. The Institute's goals were to upgrade teachers' skills in the sciences and in math and to increase their ability to motivate students to consider careers in these areas. The Institute trained teachers from 1957-1970. Yearbooks were compiled by the Math Dept. and included project proposals, proposed course programs, director's guidebooks, brochures, list of participants, and other documents related to the administration of the Institute.
  - Administrative Files, 1957-1970 and undated (Box 1)
    - Participants, 1957-1962 (Box 1)
    - Participants at Other Schools, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
    - NSF Participants with Degrees, 1966-1970 (Box 1)
    - Forms and Form Letters, undated (Box 1)
  - Yearbooks, 1955-1970
    - Yearbook, 1955-1956 (Box 1)
    - Yearbook I, 1957 (Box 1)
    - Yearbook II, 1957 (Box 1)
    - Yearbook I, 1958 (Box 1)
    - Yearbook II, 1958 (Box 1)
    - Yearbook III, 1958 (Box 1)
    - Yearbook I, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Yearbook II, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Yearbook I, 1960 (Box 1)
    - Yearbook II, 1960 (Box 1)
    - Yearbook III, 1960 (Box 1)
    - Yearbook IV, 1960 (Box 1)
    - Yearbook I, 1961 (Box 2)
    - Yearbook III, 1961 (Box 2)
    - Yearbook I, 1962 (Box 2)
    - Yearbook IV, 1962 (Box 2)
    - Yearbook I, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Yearbook, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Yearbook, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Yearbook I, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Yearbook III, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Yearbook I, 1965 (Box 2)
    - Yearbook II, 1965 (Box 2)
    - Yearbook IV, 1965 (Box 2)
    - Yearbook I, 1966 (Box 2)
    - Yearbook II, 1966 (Box 2)
    - Yearbook IV, 1966 (Box 3)
    - Yearbook I, 1967 (Box 3)
    - Yearbook II, 1967 (Box 3)
    - Yearbook, 1968 (Box 3)
    - Yearbook, 1968 (Box 3)
    - Yearbook, 1968 (Box 3)
    - Yearbook, A-N, 1969 (Box 3)
    - Yearbook, O-Z, 1969 (Box 3)
    - Yearbook, 1970 (Box 3)
- Retired Officer Program, 1957-1971 and undated
  The Retired Officer Program, supported by the National Science Foundation, was set up to retrain retired Armed Services officers to teach mathematics in high school or at the introductory college level. This program was a graduate level course at Duke University and lead to a degree of Master of Arts in Teaching. The program ran from 1958-1967.
  - Administrative Records (Box 4)
    - Correspondence and Reports, 1957-1960 (Box 4)
    - Survey of Past Participants, 1958-1962 (Box 4)
    - Copies of Brochures, 1959-1966 (Box 4)
    - Reports to the National Science Foundation, 1960-1964 (Box 4)
    - Participants, 1961-1966 (Box 4)
      Includes photographs.
    - Form Letters, 1961-1971 and undated (Box 4)
    - Minutes of the National Science Board Meeting, Jan. 18-19, 1962 (Box 4)
    - Minutes of the National Science Board Meeting, March 15-16, 1962 (Box 4)
    - Veterans Administration, 1966 (Box 4)
  - Program Records, July 1957-July 1964
    - 1957-1962 (Box 4)
    - 1962-1963 (Box 4)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 4)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 4)
    - 1957-1960 (Box 4)
    - 1957-1962 (Box 4)
    - 1957-1962 (Box 4)
    - 1958-1959 (Box 4)
    - 1958-1960 (Box 4)
    - 1959-1960 (Box 4)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 4)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 5)
      Includes photograph of class of 1962.
    - 1962-1963 (Box 5)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 5)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 5)
    - 1967 (Box 5)